how big are they? How much room is that? How many server racks could you fit in there? And for some data centers, you might get two of these pieces of information. You know how much they spent, and they also, say, because they had to contract with the local government to get the power provided, you might know what they made a deal to buy, so you know how much power it takes. Then you can look at the ratios of those numbers, and figure out for a data center where you don't have that information, you can figure out, but maybe you only have one of those, you know the square footage, then you could figure out well, maybe the power is proportional. And you can do this same thing with a lot of different quantities, you know, with guesses about the total amount of storage, the number of servers, the number of drives per server, and in each case using what you know to come up with a model that narrows down your guesses for the things that you don't know. It's sort of circling around the number you're trying to get. And this is a lot of fun. The math is not all that advanced, and really it's like nothing more than solving a sudoku puzzle. So what I did, I went through all of this information, spent a day or two researching. And there are some things I didn't look at. You could always look at the Google recruitment messages that they post. That gives you an idea of where they have people. Sometimes, when people visit a data center, they'll take a cell-cam photo and post it, and they aren't supposed to, but you can learn things about their hardware that way. And in fact, you can just look at pizza delivery drivers. Turns out, they know where all the Google data centers are, at least the ones that have people in them. But I came up with my estimate, which I felt pretty good about, that was about 10 exabytes of data across all of Google's operations, and then another maybe five exabytes or so of offline storage in tape drives, which it turns out Google is about the world's largest consumer of. So I came up with this estimate, and this is a staggering amount of data. It's quite a bit more than any other organization in the world has, as far as we know. There's a couple of other contenders, especially everyone always thinks of the NSA. But using some of these same methods, we can look at the NSA's data centers, and figure out, you know, we don't know what's going on there, but it's pretty clear that their operation is not the size of Google's. Adding all of this up, I came up with the other thing that we can answer, which is, how many punch cards would this take? And so a punch card can hold about 80 characters, and you can fit about 2,000 or so cards into a box, and you put them in, say, my home region of New England, it would cover the entire region up to a depth of a little less than five kilometers, which is about three times deeper than the glaciers during the last ice age about 20,000 years ago. So this is impractical, but I think that's about the best answer I could come up with. And I posted it on my website. I wrote it up. And I didn't expect to get an answer from Google, because of course they've been so secretive, they didn't answer of my questions, and so I just put it up and said, well, I guess we'll never know. But then a little while later I got a message, a couple weeks later, from Google, saying, hey, someone here has an envelope for you. So I go and get it, open it up, and it's punch cards. (Laughter) Google-branded punch cards. And on these punch cards, there are a bunch of holes, and I said, thank you, thank you, okay, so what's on here? So I get some software and start reading it, and scan them, and it turns out it's a puzzle. There's a bunch of code, and I get some friends to help, and we crack the code, and then inside that is another code, and then there are some equations, and then we solve those equations, and then finally out pops a message from Google which is their official answer to my article, and it said, "No comment." (Laughter) (Applause) And I love calculating these kinds of things, and it's not that I love doing the math. I do a lot of math, but I don't really like math for its own sake. What I love is that it lets you take some things that you know, and just by moving symbols around on a piece of paper, find out something that you didn't know that's very surprising. And I have a lot of stupid questions, and I love that math gives the power to answer them sometimes. And sometimes not. This is a question I got from a reader, an anonymous reader, and the subject line just said, "Urgent," and this was the entire email: "If people had wheels and could fly, how would we differentiate them from airplanes?" Urgent. (Laughter) And I think there are some questions that math just cannot answer. Thank you. (Applause)
¿qué tan grandes son? ¿Cuánto espacio es eso? ¿Cuántos servidores podrías encajar allí? Y para algunos centros de datos, se podrían conseguir dos de esas piezas de información. Se sabe cuánto gastaron, y también, por ejemplo, dado que tenían que contratar con el gobierno local para obtener la potencia suministrada, se podría saber que hicieron un trato para comprar, así que se sabe la energía que usan. Entonces se puede ver las proporciones de esos números, y averiguar para un centro de datos en la que no se tiene esa información, averiguar, pero tal vez solo se tenga uno de esos, digamos los metros cuadrados, entonces se puede averiguar bueno, tal vez la potencia es proporcional. Se puede hacer lo mismo con diferentes cantidades, con conjeturas de la cantidad total de almacenamiento, el número de servidores, el número de unidades por servidor, y en cada caso usando lo que se sabe para llegar a un modelo que reduzca las conjeturas sobre las cosas que no se saben. Es como girar en torno al número al que se quiere llegar. Y es muy divertido. La matemática no es tan avanzada, y realmente es nada más que como resolver un sudoku. Así que eso hice, con toda esta información, pasé un día o dos investigando. Hay un par de cosas que no consideré. Siempre se pueden ver los mensajes de reclutamiento que Google publica. Eso da una idea de dónde tienen personal. A veces, cuando la gente los visita, toma fotografías y las publica, y se supone que no deberían de hacerlo, pero así se puede aprender cosas sobre su hardware. Y, de hecho, se pueden examinar los repartidores de pizza. Resulta que ellos saben dónde están todos los centros de datos de Google, al menos los que tienen personas en ellos. Pero presenté mi estimación, con la que me sentía muy bien, que había unos 10 exabytes de datos en todas las operaciones de Google, y luego otros quizás 5 exabytes o así de almacenamiento fuera de línea en cinta, donde resulta que Google es el consumidor más grande del mundo. Así que presenté esta estimación, y esta es una cantidad asombrosa de datos. Es bastante más de lo que cualquier otra organización tiene en el mundo, hasta donde sabemos. Hay un par de competidores, especialmente todo el mundo siempre piensa en la NSA. Pero usando estos mismos métodos, podemos mirar a los centros de datos de la NSA, y deducir, ya saben, no sabemos lo que pasa allí, pero está bastante claro que su funcionamiento no es del tamaño de Google. Sumando todo, propuse la otra cosa que podemos responder, que es, ¿cuántas tarjetas perforadas se necesitarían? Una tarjeta perforada puede contener alrededor de 80 caracteres, y pueden caber alrededor de más o menos 2000 tarjetas en una caja, y se ponen en, digamos, mi tierra natal, Nueva Inglaterra, cubriría la región por completo hasta una profundidad de un poco menos de cinco kilómetros, casi 3 veces más profundo que los glaciares durante la última era de hielo hace unos 20 000 años. Esto es poco práctico, pero creo esa es la mejor respuesta que podía dar. Y la publiqué en mi sitio web. Escribí al respecto. Y no esperaba una respuesta de Google, porque han sido tan reservados, no respondieron a mis preguntas, y así que solo lo puse y dije, bueno, supongo que nunca lo sabremos. Pero un poco más tarde recibí un mensaje de Google, diciendo, ey, alguien aquí tiene un sobre para usted. Así que voy por él, lo abro, y son tarjetas perforadas. (Risas) Tarjetas perforadas marca Google. Y en esas tarjetas perforadas, hay una serie de agujeros, y dije, gracias, gracias, bien, ¿qué hay aquí? Conseguí un software y empecé a leerlas, y analizarlas, y resulta que es un rompecabezas. Hay un montón de código, pedí ayuda a unos amigos, desciframos el código, y luego había otro código dentro, y luego algunas ecuaciones, resolvimos esas ecuaciones, finalmente, aparece un mensaje de Google que es su respuesta oficial a mi artículo, y decía, "Sin comentarios". (Risas) (Aplausos) Me encanta calcular este tipo de cosas, y no es que me encante hacer cálculos. Hago mucho de matemáticas, pero no me gustan mucho en sí mismas. Lo que me gusta es que te permiten tomar algunas cosas que sabes, y solo con mover símbolos sobre un pedazo de papel, encontrar algo que no sabías que es sorprendente. Recibo muchas preguntas estúpidas, y me encanta que las matemáticas tengan el poder para responderlas algunas veces. Y algunas veces no. Esta es una pregunta de un lector, un lector anónimo, y el asunto decía, "Urgente", y este fue todo el email: "Si la gente tuviera ruedas y pudiera volar, ¿cómo nos diferenciaríamos de los aviones?" Urgente. (Risas) Pienso que hay algunas preguntas que las matemáticas simplemente no pueden responder. Gracias. (Aplausos)